Finding Aid for the Albert E. Smith Papers LSC.2004
UCLA Library Special Collections
Albert E. Smith papers
1897-1933
UCLA Library Special Collections
Smith, Albert E.
LSC.2004
18 Linear Feet (15 boxes, 6 oversize boxes)
Albert E. Smith (1875-1958) co-founded the Vitagraph Company of America as the Reader, Smith, and Blackton Combination in 1894. He invented the Vitagraph, one of the first successful motion picture projectors, in 1896. The collection consists of correspondence, scrapbooks, albums, photographs, auditor's reports, and trade agreements pertaining to the business of the Vitagraph Company of America, of which Smith was co-founder.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
CONTAINS AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS: This collection contains processed audiovisual materials. All requests to access digital materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of Lucile Smith, 1959.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9929769273606533
Biography
Smith was born in 1875 in Faversham, England; co-founded the Vitagraph Company of America as the Reader, Smith, and Blackton Combination in 1894; Vitagraph producer, writer, and executive with actor and director J. Stuart Blackton until sale of the company to Warner Brothers in 1925; invented the Vitagraph, one of the first successful motion picture projectors, in 1896; had a wife, Lucile, and 6 children; died August 1, 1958 in Los Angeles.
Scope and Content
Collection consists of correspondence, scrapbooks, albums, photographs, auditor's reports, and trade agreements pertaining to the business of the Vitagraph Company of America, of which Smith was co-founder. Runs of ephemeral publications, Vitagraph releases (1916-1920) and six bound volumes of the Vitagraph Bulletin (1906-1916) complete the Vitagraph documentation. There are 17 reels of audiotapes recorded by Smith on the subject of motion picture history, as well as a copy of his autobiography.
Organization and Arrangement
Arranged in the following series:
Collection arranged chronologically.
Motion picture industry -- History -- Archives.; Motion picture producers and directors -- United States -- Archives.; Scrapbooks.; Photographs.; Audiotapes.; Blackton, James Stuart; Smith, Albert E.--Archives.; Vitagraph Company of America--Archives.; Vitagraph Company of America.
- Early beginnings., 1897-1904.; 291pp. (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Newspaper clippings, documents, early film catalogs (1901-1904), folder of notes for book and typescript manuscripts of history of Vitagraph Company by Albert E. Smith.
  - Tape I Albert E. Smith, early 1949 recorded from tape 1, 2015 December 2; yrlsc_2004_01_01a; 1 Sound Recordings (1 1/4 inch audiotape; Duration: 00:07:42) 7 inches (Box 1, Case 1)
    Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
    CONTAINS AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS: Audiovisual materials are available for access. All requests to access digital materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
    Scope and Contents
    Transcribed from container: "Tape I Speed 7 1/2 Albert E. Smith, early 1949, both sides, recorded from tape 1 in Albert E. Smith Papers, Box 14."; Conent note: Starts w/ Smith interview. Two other recordings on this track, may or may not be related.
  - Tape I Albert E. Smith, early 1949 recorded from tape 1, 2015 December 2; yrlsc_2004_01_01b; 1 Sound Recordings (1 1/4 inch audiotape; Duration: 00:30:46) 7 inches (Box 1, Case 1)
    Transcribed from container: "Tape I Speed 7 1/2 Albert E. Smith, early 1949, both sides, recorded from tape 1 in Albert E. Smith Papers, Box 14."
  - Tape II Albert E. Smith early 1949 rerecorded from tapes 2, 3, 4, 5, 2015 December 1; yrlsc_2004_01_02a; 1 Sound Recordings (1 1/4 inch audiotape; Duration: 01:01:00) 7 inches (Box 1, Case 2)
    Transcribed from container: "Tape II Speed 3 3/4 Albert E. Smith, early 1949, both sides, rerecorded from tapes 2, 3, 4, 5 in Albert E. Smith Papers, Box 14." "Original of side 2, 1st half was spliced several times. May sound a bit patchy in places."
  - Tape II Albert E. Smith early 1949 rerecorded from tapes 2, 3, 4, 5, 2015 December 1; yrlsc_2004_01_02b; 1 Sound Recordings (1 1/4 inch audiotape; Duration: 01:01:00) 7 inches (Box 1, Case 2)
  - Tape III Albert E. Smith early 1949 rerecorded from tapes 6, 7, 8, 9, 2015 December 1; yrlsc_2004_01_03a; 1 Sound Recordings (1 1/4 inch audiotape; Duration: 01:01:00) 7 inches (Box 1, Case 3)
    Transcribed from container: "Tape III Speed 3 3/4 Albert E. Smith, early 1949, both sides, rerecorded from tapes 6, 7, 8, 9 in Albert E. Smith Papers, Box 14."
  - Tape III Albert E. Smith early 1949 rerecorded from tapes 6, 7, 8, 9, 2015 December 1; yrlsc_2004_01_03b; 1 Sound Recordings (1 1/4 inch audiotape; Duration: 00:59:55) 7 inches (Box 1, Case 3)
  - Tape IV Albert E. Smith early 1949 rerecorded from tapes 10, 11, 12, 13, 2015 December 1; yrlsc_2004_01_04a; 1 Sound Recordings (1 1/4 inch audiotape; Duration: 01:01:00) 7 inches (Box 1, Case 4)
    Transcribed from container: "Tape IV Speed 3 3/4 Albert E. Smith, early 1949, both sides, rerecorded from tapes 10, 11, 12, 13 in Albert E. Smith Papers, Box 14."
  - Tape IV Albert E. Smith early 1949 rerecorded from tapes 10, 11, 12, 13, 2015 December 2; yrlsc_2004_01_04b; 1 Sound Recordings (1 1/4 inch audiotape; Duration: 01:01:00) 7 inches (Box 1, Case 4)
  - Tape V Albert E. Smith early 1949, side 1 only rerecorded from tapes 14 & 15, 2015 December 2; yrlsc_2004_01_05; 1 Sound Recordings (1 1/4 inch audiotape; Duration: 01:03:00) 7 inches (Box 1, Case 5)
    Transcribed from container: "Tape V Speed 3 3/4 Albert E. Smith early 1949, side 1 only rerecorded from tapes 14 & 15 (both labeled 14-a) in Albert E. Smith Papers, Box 14"
- 1908-1916. (Box 2)
  Correspondence, ephemera and clippings, auditor's reports, stock certificates, agreements (bound volume) re ownership of Vitagraph Company and By-Laws of Smith-Blackton Company, 1916.
- Vitagraph Bulletins., 1909-1916.; Six bound volumes. (Box 3)
- 1916. (Box 4)
  Correspondence, contracts, auditor's statements. The Big Four Family, publication of Vitagraph, Lubin, Selig, Essanay, Incorporated. Bound (vol.1-4).
- 1915-1918. (Box 5)
  Correspondence, legal documents; Vitagraph Releases. 1916-1917 (two bound volumes). Vitagraph family, vol.9-12. June 1917-June 1918 (bound).
- 1917-1920. (Box 6)
  Correspondence, legal documents, auditor's reports. Vitagraph Releases. 1918, 1919 (two bound volumes). Shadowland, the magazine of magazines. (M.P. Publishing Company, New York). vol.1 no.1. September 1919.
- 1920-1922. (Box 7)
  Correspondence, contracts and agreements, copies of legal briefs involving Vitagraph Company, auditor's reports. Typescript of Releases 1920 (bound) containing synopses and credits.
- 1923-1924. (Box 8)
  Legal documents, correspondence.
- 1924-1929. (Box 9)
  Correspondence, publicity releases.
- 1925-1956. (Box 10)
  Correspondence, ephemera, photographs, auditor's report 1917.Two reels and a crank. Autographed copy of book.
- Notebooks containing story ideas. Reports on individual theatres. Legal contracts., 1920. 1924. (Box 11)
- Stills. (Box 12, Box 15)
- Scrapbook of clippings on the death of John Bunny., 1915. (Box 13)
- Scrapbook of newspaper clippings., 1914. (Box 13)
- Miscellaneous motion-picture publications. (Box 13)
- History of Vitagraph Company., 17 reels tape. (Box 14)
- Photograph album. Stills from Vitagraph productions of O'Henry stories. (Box 16)
- Photograph album. Jean Paige - stills from Vitagraph productions. (Box 16)
- Album of stills. (Box 17, Box 18, Box 19)
- Scrapbook., 1925. (Box 20)
  Newspaper clippings covering Vitagraph's break with Hays Office (MPPDA).
- Scrapbook. Clippings., 1923-1933. (Box 20)
- Panoramic photograph of Vitagraph personnel., 1910. (Box 21)
  General note
  Missing, January 1990.